[Music]
so I'm going to
Define an operator a linear operator called
LP okay so LP is something uh that's going to
take a vector from the space V where capital
V is the space of all value functions right
so capital V is a complete normed Vector
space of all value functions right so I'm
going I'm going to Define an operator L Pi that
takes an element in V to another element in V
right so how I Define l Pi L Pi operating
on V will give me back a function that is
right so V is some element in capital V it's a
some value function okay or rather some element
in capital V okay so what's the difference between
saying that is some value function and then saying
some element in capital B when it say it's a value
function I'm kind of implicitly saying that there
is a policy for which that is the expected return
right right but when I say it's a point in the
space V that need not necessarily be true I
mean it's just some point in a s dimensional
space that need not necessarily exist exist a
policy corresponding to that function okay so
I'm just saying it's some function V right
that ends in exists in that space capital
V what is the right hand side space V to v v to V
other space what other space space V2 V yeah right
does that make sense I mean is that confusing
to people yes everybody is on board right
good right so what does my
uh bman equation tell me if
you think about it the Melman equation tells me
right that's what my bman equation is telling me
essentially it's saying that I take this point V
Pi in the space capital V I apply the operator
L Pi on it whatever it gives me back will be V
PI right so likewise if I can define an
operator for the optimality equation it
will tell me that V Star is a point
in space V say that if I apply the
operator let's call it l if I apply
L on it it will give me back V Star
so this implies
that V Pi is what is known as a fixed point of
L PI right so I so if you think about it right
so normally I take some vector v I apply L
Pi on it okay it'll go to some other point
then I'll apply LP on it it'll go to some
other point then I'll apply LP on it it'll
keep moving around right in space right if I
apply LP on it and it stays there then I call
it a fixed Point what uh because I'm using
the I'm defining the operator through R pi
and P Pi which themselves are defined
through PI right I mean if you looked
at if you remember the independent of no it's
not because mapping is r p i mean mapping Ed
R pi and P pi as integral components of it
right so it's not independent so the other one
is independent there we'll drop the dependence
the optimality equation has no dependence on
Pi there we'll drop the dependence on Pi but the
belman equation has a that's the P init okay great
so we introduce you to something called
The banak Fix Point theorem okay this a
very basic I mean believe it or not whatever we
are doing is very very fundamental stuff right
very minimal minimal math in terms of trying to
prove convergence and things like that because
I have restricted you to finite mdps okay so
the the more Harry the more interesting math
comes when you start operating in the infinite
State spaces right uh where uh I mean you can't
write down simple results okay you have to have
lot of qualifications if your mdp says that yes
satisfies this and that and that and a satisfies
this and that and that then something will hold
right but here we can say some we can write very
easy results so I'm going to use something called
the banak fixon theorem okay which will
uh which makes our life a lot easy right
sounds like a very fancy term right
banak space so what is a banak
space we already know what a banak space
is complete normed Vector space is
called a banak space just don't get
put off by by terminology we understand
this right so we know what a banak space
is a complete nored Vector space is a banak space
right H so one thing which I forgot
I'll introduce it lat this now okay
[Music]
so some mapping T that Maps points in U to another
point in U right um assume it's a contraction
mapping I'll tell you what is a contraction
mapping in a minute okay but you can think kind
of guess what a contraction mapping is right it
takes two points in space right I take u and v i
take T of U and I take T of V right so T of U and
T of V will be close to each other than u and v
were okay so that's essentially contraction
mapping so I'll write it down formally in a minute
right then
for
[Music]
okay so what we are saying suppose U is a Bak
space and T is a contraction mapping essentially
things that brings points together uh then
there exist a unique V Star in U such that
T V Star equal to V Star so that essentially
means that that t has a fixed Point T has a
fixed point and it is a unique fixed Point
okay and the second thing is for arbitrary
starting point V if I keep repeatedly
applying t on V right I'll converge to V
St right so showing one does not imply two
okay just because the fixed Point exists
right repeatedly applying did not necessarily
converge to the fix point in fact there are
some results for certain algorithms where we can
show that that algorithm itself has a fixed point
I mean or rather the the system of equations you
set up itself has a fixed point but the iterative
process that you are using for solving it need not
necessarily converge to it okay there are cases
that will happen but in this case it says turns
out that repeatedly applying T that's essentially
what the sequence is right I start off with v
not I apply t on it once I get V1 I apply t on it
again I get V2 I apply t on it again I get V3 and
so on so forth right I keep doing this well often
enough right I'll end up in V Star right how how
many times is often enough something we'll study
when we look at actual algorithms uh for solving
these problems uh but these are the things right
that exists a unique V Star and this there a
couple of things that we need to show one is that
use a banak space yeah why you call fixed point
isn't it like a whole line basically an Vector
of well it's a point it's a point in the V Space
right it's I Vector fine but I Vector is a point
in the v space no the point in the right that's
what we have been saying so what is V Pi V Pi is
a vector that the first component is V Pi of
one then V Pi of 2 V Pi of 3 V Pi of 4 it's
ESS simply a point in in in a s dimensional
vector space right confusing let's think of
a case where there are two states alone let's
State one state two right I Define some policy
let's I'm just going to cook up something let's
let's look at how it works I have one I have two
[Music]
okay some arbitrary thing I have written an
mdp for you here right so I take action one
from State one I'll go to state two I'll get
a reward of one I'll take action one in state
two I'll get go to state one with the reward
of one I take action two in either State one
or state two I'm going to stay there with the
reward of minus one okay now let me Define a
policy so what is a policy Pi of 1 is A1 and
Pi of 2 is A2 I determine sorry A1 Pi of 2
is A1 let's just Define A1 A1 for both right
so what is the value of uh State one under pi
I me you can do it easily enough but
[Music] uh for some value of gamma you
can solve it or you can just write the
summation right just 1 + GMA plus GMA
square + GMA Cub I mean you can solve
the system of equation or you can just
tell me what is the limit of the summation
somebody tell
me
yeah right now if I think of this in a
two dimensional space so I have a two
dimensional space this Dimension is V Pi of
1 this Dimension is V Pi of 2 just a point
so this point is this V of
one now we can think of defining
a pi Prime which is like uh
same minus of
that right so for any policy I choose like this
right Pi Pi Pi of A1 and Pi of A2 whatever things
I choose I'm going to end up with some point in
this space right so this is what I mean by the
space capital V so this is my space capital V
and each value function is a point in the space
right I mean I was hoping people had actually
this this in their mind when they are nodding
with whatever I was saying earlier right so
this is what I mean by saying all of these
things which we talked about right this being a
complete normed Vector space everything we have
talked about is with this picture in mind right so
okay does it make sense any questions about that
of course I just chose deterministic policies
to be easy right you could choose stochastic
policies you just have to write out this more
terms in this equation right this equation will
have the sum over PSA right and then you
solve it and then you get it right so it's
so essentially the tricky part here turns
out showing that whatever mapping T you are
considering is a contraction mapping so if you
can show whatever is the map that you consider
in this case we are going to be considering L
Pi if you can show that L Pi is a contraction
mapping right then you get the rest of it for
free yeah yeah so that's it essentially that's
what you have to do to show it's a conversion
uh it's it's a contraction mapping I I'll
just tell you in a minute I formally write
down what a contraction map fing us right
right so for sure okay it's it moves away it's
a this is what a contraction mapping is so if
u and v were some distance apart after I apply
t on both of them they will be closer than what
they were earlier right by a factor of at least
Lambda right where Lambda lies between 0 and 1
right one excluded okay so the smaller the value
of Lambda what does it mean the faster the points
are B together the more the contraction
is right the closer the value of Lambda
to one the lesser the contractions obviously
Lambda equal to 1 does not make sense right
if Lambda is one then there is no
contraction okay if Lambda 1 is T
identity need not be I'm just just telling
you just the distance have to be
preserved right I can swap u and v
also right just remember that
okay so now let's look at the
proof of the banak fix point so why is it
called the banak fix Point theorem there's
a fix point to which all because it applies
in b space right so for different kinds of
spaces that you are starting off with
you have different kinds of fix Point
here that's a whole family of fix Point
theorems okay depending on the underlying
assumptions you make so this is a fix
Point theorem that will show in the Bak
bace it's one of the simplest of the fix
Point theorems okay so if you have lesser
restrictions on the underlying space then
the showing fixed points becomes more tricky
okay okay so here's the trick that we'll be using
repeatedly okay I'm just taking some some iterates
in that sequence right so I've taken some VN
and some VN plus M so VN plus M occurs after VN
okay so I'm going to use the triangle INE equality
right so I can pick some arbitrary Point let us
say in between in the sequence
right so we say VN plus m by2
I can pick some arbitrary point in the sequence
which is v n + m by2 and then I can say this is
less than VN + m minus VN + m by2 + VN + m by2
minus VM right so I can write it like this right
for the time being forget about the produ they
coming from a sequence just think of them as
three points in space right so VN is some some
point in that space v m n plus m is some other
point in that space and this guy is a third
point in that space right so once I give you
three points I can use a triangle inequality right
I just chosen the third point to be somewhere in
between in the sequence Okay so so that's all
I mean nothing to do with the fact that these
three points are a sequence I can use a triangle
inequality given any three points okay so I can
do it this way right but there is nothing S
no sanctity about doing this in fact I can
split this further I can say VN plus M by2 and
then n by 4 right I can split that and do that
in fact I can do this for every step along
the way so I'm going to replace it with this
right so basically n n + 1 n + 1
n + 2 n+ 2 n+ 3 so it gives doing
this so repeatedly applied the
triangle inequality to get this
right
yeah no T takes from U to u u to U U and
then Maps another point in U cont no so
two different points right so I take
two arbitrary points U and B this for
all points u and v and U right so any
arbitrary point I take I apply t on U
and I apply t on V right so I'll get two
resulting points right so I'll take the
distance between them they should be less
than the original distance between u and
v t is a mapping from U to U it's not U cross
U to U cross U right it's mapping from U to U
okay so now we have reduced it to the same T
applied multiple times right so I can apply T
use this multiple times right so what I'm going
to get using this contraction operator here
is it
fine why T because it's decreasing what's
it in the Second Step app the operator T
because we found that it's decreasing the
distance between the two subse why did I
apply the operator T by definition we
n + k + 1 is T operating on V1 n plus K
[Music]
* does it make sense now now this quantity is
independent of K so I can take it out
and sum over okay so what is the sum
I mean very OD I keep getting calls today I don't
know why like my third call during the class
[Music]
so what can you say about this
sequence as n and M become large it become
smaller and smaller and smaller right as n
and M becomes larger and larger that sequence
is going to become smaller and smaller so this
is a constant so it doesn't matter so
n and M become larger and larger this
is going to become smaller and smaller
so what can you say the sequence VN is
kosi okay people get
that anything else we can say we assume
that's a banak space right that's why
I said banak space fix Point theorems are
easy we assume it's a banak space therefore
VN is convergent we already know that right so
what needs to be shown now [Music] [Applause]